to disrupt the agricultural food desert and begin to correct the dysfunctional food system that we've created. So maybe it seems like a really small countermeasure to a big, huge problem -- just go plant flowers -- but when bees have access to good nutrition, we have access to good nutrition through their pollination services. And when bees have access to good nutrition, they're better able to engage their own natural defenses, their healthcare, that they have relied on for millions of years. So the beauty of helping bees this way, for me, is that every one of us needs to behave a little bit more like a bee society, an insect society, where each of our individual actions can contribute to a grand solution, an emergent property, that's much greater than the mere sum of our individual actions. So let the small act of planting flowers and keeping them free of pesticides be the driver of large-scale change. On behalf of the bees, thank you. (Applause) Chris Anderson: Thank you. Just a quick question. The latest numbers on the die-off of bees, is there any sign of things bottoming out? What's your hope/depression level on this? Maria Spivak: Yeah. At least in the United States, an average of 30 percent of all bee hives are lost every winter. About 20 years ago, we were at a 15-percent loss. So it's getting precarious. CA: That's not 30 percent a year, that's -- MS: Yes, thirty percent a year. CA: Thirty percent a year. MS: But then beekeepers are able to divide their colonies and so they can maintain the same number, they can recuperate some of their loss. We're kind of at a tipping point. We can't really afford to lose that many more. We need to be really appreciative of all the beekeepers out there. Plant flowers. CA: Thank you. (Applause)
pour rompre le désert alimentaire agricole et commencer à corriger ce système alimentaire dysfonctionnel que nous avons créé. Cela peut sembler être une très petite réponse à un gros, un énorme problème, de juste planter des fleurs. Mais quand les abeilles ont accès à une bonne nourriture, nous avons accès à une bonne nourriture grâce à leurs actions de pollinisation. Quand les abeilles ont accès à une bonne nourriture, elles peuvent mieux mobiliser leurs propres défenses naturelles, leur service de santé, dont elles dépendent depuis des millions d'années. La beauté de cette façon d'aider les abeilles, pour moi, c'est que chacun d'entre nous doit se comporter un petit peu plus comme une société d'abeilles, une société d'insectes, où chacune de nos actions individuelles peut contribuer à une solution d'ensemble, une propriété émergente, qui est bien plus que la simple somme de nos actions individuelles. Faisons en sorte que le modeste acte de planter des fleurs et de les préserver des pesticides soit le moteur d'un changement à grande échelle. Au nom des abeilles, merci. (Applaudissements) Chris Anderson : Merci. Juste une question rapide. Les derniers chiffres de l'extinction des abeilles, y a-t-il des signes indiquant un fléchissement ? Quel est votre niveau d'espoir/dépression à ce sujet ? Maria Spivak : Oui. Aux États-Unis, en tout cas, nous perdons en moyenne 30 % de nos ruches chaque hiver. Il y a 20 ans, nous en étions à 15 % de pertes. Alors ça devient précaire. C. A. : Ce n'est pas 30 % par an, c'est... M. S. : Oui, c'est 30 % par an. C. A. : 30 % par an ! M. S. : Oui, mais les apiculteurs peuvent diviser leurs colonies et ainsi maintenir leur nombre, ils peuvent recouvrer une partie de leurs pertes. Nous en sommes à un tournant, en fait. Nous ne pouvons pas vraiment nous permettre d'en perdre beaucoup plus. Nous devons être vraiment reconnaissants envers tous ces apiculteurs. Plantez des fleurs. C. A. : Merci. (Applaudissements)